Alan Guedes — C.V.

London – UK

Shorbio

I am a Computer Scientist (PhD & Postdoc) interested in geometric Machine Learning (ML) for the next generation of immersive and multimedia systems. My career can be seen threefold. In research, I worked in research projects on Multimedia & ML and contributed to its community (Springer, ACM SIGMM and SBC WebMedia). In industry, some done research was transferred through opensource and standards at TV forums (ITU-T SG16 and BR TV Forum). And in teaching, I co-supervised students, acted as a lecturer on underand post- graduate courses, and organized workshops to promote student interest in public engagement.

Experiences

Work

UCL, LASP Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML project

2021-today

Highlights: ACM SIGMM committees and workshop organizer; co-supervised undergrad students.

- SpheryStream project funded by EPSRC to Improve 360-video streaming with profile-based methods

PUC-Rio. TeleMidia Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML & Multimedia projects

2017-2020

Highlights: project PI; team leader; standards contributions; SBC WebMedia committees and workshop organizer (students for social impact); co-supervised under/postgrad students; postgraduate lecturer assistant.

- VideoMR project, funded by Microsoft & RNP to detect inappropriate content in video scenes;
- AML (Anti-Money Laundry) project funded by BTG Bank to detect financial transctions risk and anomaly detection;
- GT-RAP project funded by RNP to develop a blockchain-based system for academic certificates.

Dynavideo, TV Division

Software engineer
Highlights: multiple awarded social impact project.

2012-2012

Brasil4D project funded by World Bank to transmit interactive TV content with social features to low-income families.
 Its results were published in a public report

Education

PUC-Rio

PhD. in Informatics. Thesis on Multimodal-multiuser support in multimedia scene descriptions 2013–2017 Highlights: thesis concepts used in SBTVD standard; industry committees.

- PUC-Rio Ginga reference implementation, funded by PUC-Rio Software Licenses to TV manufacturers;
- From SBTVD Conformance Test Suite for TV manufacturers

UFPB

MSc. in Informatics. Thesis on Multi-device support in TV app stores

2010-2012

Highlights: thesis concepts used in the awarded Brasil4D project; undergraduate lecturer; project leader

- GingaAppStore, funded by RNP, to design a broadband system to deliver TV applications;
- Art TVDI, funded by RNP, to design agile methods for TV applications development;

UFPB

BSc. in Computer Science. Final report on Component-based architecture for TV middleware 2005–2009

- $\operatorname{\mathsf{Ginga}}$ CDN, funded by RNP, to develop reusable TV middleware components.
- Tutor on Analysis and design of Algorithms;
- Part-Time software developer at Dynavideo TV Division to prototype TV software in ST boards.

Research

Publications

Google Scholar shows >50 published papers, >100 citations, h-index 6. See below recent and some selected publications.

Elsevier Book Chapter 2022

ACM Multimedia Systems. Springer Journal on Multimedia Tools and Applications.	2022 2016, 2020
IEEE Symposium on Multimedia (ISM).	2020
SBC WebMedia 2020, 2020, 2020, 2021	1, 2021, 2021
ACM Symposium on Document Engineering.	2019
IEEE Multimedia Signal Processing.	2019
Committees	
ACM, Special Interest Group on Multimedia	
Reviewer and chairing - Multimedia conference: reviewer (2022), area chair (2022), reproducibility chair (2023) - Multimedia Systems (ACM MM): MMVE review (2021, 2022, 2023) and demo chair (2022) - Immersive Experiences (ACM IMX) conference: reviewer (2022) and area chair (2022) - QoMex conference (ACM QoMEX): reviewer (2023)	2020-today
BR Computing Society (SBC), Web&Mulimedia Commitee	
Steering Committee	2021-today
Reviewer and chairing - WebMedia conference reviewer (2017-today), chair of Undergrad workshop (2018), chair of Dem (2019-2022), and chair of Social Impact Workshop (2019-2022)	2017-today nos Workshop
Springer Reviewer	2022 to day
- Journal of Multimedia Tools and Applications: reviewer (2022, 2023)	2022-today
- Iberoamerican Conference on TV Applications and Usability: reviewer (2020, 2021, 2022)	
Brazilian TV Forum (SBTVD) Academic member at Technical Module contributing to TV middleware standards	2017-2021
International Telecommunication Union (ITU)	2017 2021
Academic member at SG - $16/Q13$ contributing to IPTV middleware standards	2017-2021
Teaching	
UCL	2022 today
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.	2022-today
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia	·
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.	2022-today 2018-2022
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.	·
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio	2018-2022
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency	2018-2022 2019 2013
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>	2018-2022 2019 2013
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>RNP ESR	2018-2022 2019 2013 -30) 2012
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30)	2018-2022 2019 2013
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>RNP ESR	2018-2022 2019 2013 -30) 2012 2011
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30) UFPB	2018-2022 2019 2013 -30) 2012 2011
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30) UFPB Lecturer (and course design) on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students	2018-2022 2019 2013 -30) 2012 2011 s (>15) 2010
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30) UFPB Lecturer (and course design) on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students Funding & Awards	2018-2022 2019 2013 -30) 2012 2011 s (>15) 2010
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30) UFPB Lecturer (and course design) on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students. Funding & Awards Funding	2018-2022 2019 2013 -30) 2012 2011 s (>15) 2010
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30) UFPB Lecturer (and course design) on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students Funding & Awards Funding Microsoft&RNP	2018-2022 2019 2013 -30) 2012 2011 s (>15) 2010
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (>RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30) UFPB Lecturer (and course design) on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students Funding & Awards Funding Microsoft&RNP Approved as PI in VideoMR project Awards ACM	2018-2022 2019 2013 -30) 2012 2011 s (>15) 2010
UCL Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects. SBC WebMedia Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research. PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30) Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30). Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals (> RNP ESR Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30) UFPB Lecturer (and course design) on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students Funding & Awards Funding. Microsoft&RNP Approved as PI in VideoMR project Awards.	2018-2022 2019 2013 -30) 2012 2011 s (>15) 2010

SIGWeb Travel Award for DocEng	2019	
Multiple TV associations		
FRIDA Innovative TV technological solutions award for Brasil4D project	2014	
SET Conference award on Best TV interactivity solution for Brasil4D project	2013	
PremioTV on Innovation and Creativity for Brasil4D project	2013	
ITU IPTV Application Challenge User-friendliness for GingaStore	2012	
Skills		
Academic: Execute research agenda. Scientific and standard writting.		
Teaching: Course design. Presentation skills.		
Programing : Python, TensorFlow, Bash, C++, Lua, Java, JavaScript, Latex, Docker.		
Social : Good and empathic communication. Positive, make-it-happen, teamwork, lead-by-example attitudes.		
Languages: Portuguese (mother tongue), English (fluent), and Spanish (fluent).		
Training		
UCL		
Data Protection for Researchers; Fundamentals in Research Funding.	2022-2023	
Nature		
Interpreting Scientific Results; Focus on Peer Review.	2022-2023	
ITU		
ITU-T A.1: Working Methods of ITU-T Study Groups	2023	

References

- Laura Toni, I.toni@ucl.ac.uk. Postdoc supervisor at UCL.
- Simone DJ Barbosa, simone@inf.puc-rio.br. PhD supervisor at PUC-Rio.
- Marcelo Moreno, moreno@ice.ufjf.br. ITU SG-16/Q13 and SBTVD collaborator.
- $\ Roberto \ Azevedo, \ roberto. azevedo @disneyresearch.com. \ Tele Midia \ collaborator.$